Eleanor Copenhaver Anderson Papers, 1901-1993 (bulk 1922-55)
Sophia Smith Collection
Eleanor Copenhaver Anderson papers
1901-1993
1922-55
Anderson, Eleanor Copenhaver, d. 1985
MS 622
3 boxes (1.25 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
YWCA worker, Labor reform advocate. The papers are primarily related to her professional and public life and focus on her work for the YWCA of the U.S.A. Types of materials include correspondence; writings; photographs; press releases; reports; journal and newspaper articles; transcripts of interviews; and memorabilia. Included is a copy of her 1933 Columbia masters thesis on working women in San Francisco. The correspondence is revealing of Anderson's intensely religious family background. Of particular note is a small amount of revealing behind-the-scenes correspondence between YWCA staff members, and a small amount of Sherwood Anderson scholar Charles Modlin's research materials on Eleanor.
Eleanor Gladys Copenhaver was born on June 15, 1896 in Marion, Virginia, to Bascom Eugene and Laura Lu Scherer Copenhaver.
Laura Lu's father founded Marion Female College, which was located next door to the family home, "Rosemont." Laura Lu attended Marion College and later taught English there. Her husband, B.E. Copenhaver, first taught at Marion and then became Smyth County superintendent of schools. In addition, Laura Lu was very active in the Lutheran Church and on the local social scene. She wrote pageants, poetry, and articles for the church and a variety of magazines. She also helped provide employment for local rural women when she founded Rosemont Industries, which marketed mountain handicrafts.
Copenhaver first attended Marion College, then transferred to Westhampton College in Richmond, Virginia, where she earned a B.A. in English in 1917. She taught high school English in Richmond for the 1917-18 school year, then enrolled in the certificate program in Social Economy and Social Research at Bryn Mawr College. In the summer of 1919 she was Camp Director for the New York College Settlement. Bryn Mawr awarded her a certificate in social economy in 1920. Copenhaver joined the national staff of the YWCA in September 1920 as a Field Secretary in the South and Central region. From 1920 to 1923 she primarily worked in rural communities organizing programs, studying conditions, and "interpreting" the Association to public gatherings and church and school groups. She switched to a specialization in industrial communities beginning in 1923, first working in the Central Region, then as National Industrial Secretary based at headquarters in New York City beginning in 1925. She completed a masters degree in political economy at Columbia University in 1933.
The writer Sherwood Anderson began spending summers in Smyth County, Virginia, in the 1920s. He came to know the Copenhaver family after he purchased two small local newspapers. First befriending Laura Lu, Anderson met Eleanor in 1928 when she was visiting from New York. Still married to his third wife at the time, Anderson began following Copenhaver on her travels for the YWCA, eventually convincing her to marry him. They were wed on July 6, 1933, in Virginia.
From 1937 to 1947 Copenhaver Anderson was head of the National YWCA's Industrial Program. She continued to travel extensively for her job, which provided the main financial support for the couple and for various family members through the Depression. Some have speculated that this, Sherwood Anderson's fourth marriage, lasted as long as it did in part because Eleanor was away so much. He died in 1941.
As the National YWCA began to drastically reduce its programs for employed women, Anderdson accepted a two-year assignment with the Foreign Division, departing for Italy in 1947. There she worked on a cooperative program between the YWCA and Amalgamated Clothing Workers, and served as an advisor to the YWCA of Italy on relief projects and employed women's programs.
While Anderson was in Italy, attacks on the YWCA for its supposed communist leanings became especially virulent. Copenhaver Anderson's name was among the many YWCA staff-particularly those in the Industrial Department--accused of communist ties in the 1948 booklet "Behind the Lace Curtains of the YWCA." In Italy, she made the mistake of authorizing an unsecured loan of YWCA funds which were lost when the individual to whom she made the loan disappeared.
After her return to the U.S., Copenhaver Anderson was terminated rather abruptly in 1950 when the YWCA of the U.S.A. eliminated its programs for employed women. During her forced leisure, she organized and transferred Sherwood Anderson's papers to the Newberry Library in Chicago.
Copenhaver Anderson was rehired in 1951 under the auspices of the YWCA and United Community Defense Services, an agency formed from fifteen social service organizations to provide short-term "health, welfare, and recreation services" to rapidly-growing communities near defense industries. She retired from the YWCA-UCDS work in 1961.
In retirement, Copenhaver Anderson spent winters in New York City and summers at "Rosemont" and "Ripshin" in Virginia. She graciously greeted Sherwood Anderson scholars and encouraged their work on her late-husband.
Eleanor Copenhaver Anderson died on September 12, 1985 in Marion, Virginia.
The Eleanor Copenhaver Anderson Papers consist of one linear foot and are primarily related to her professional and public life, dating from 1901 to 1993. Types of materials include correspondence; writings; photographs; press releases; reports; journal and newspaper articles; transcripts of interviews; and memorabilia.
The bulk of the papers date from 1922 to 1955 and focus on Copenhaver Anderson's work for the YWCA of the U.S.A. Included among the Biographical Materials in SERIES I is a fairly extensive file of clippings giving a sense of Anderson's busy travel schedule as well as a copy of her 1933 Columbia masters thesis on working women in San Francisco. The correspondence in SERIES II is revealing of Anderson's intensely religious family background. The letters written by Eleanor to Sherwood Anderson in 1932 before their marriage give a sense of the circles in which they moved and of the stressful life of a YWCA staffer. Of particular note in the YWCA materials in SERIES III. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES is a small amount of revealing behind-the-scenes correspondence between YWCA staff members. SERIES IV. consists of a small amount of Sherwood Anderson scholar Charles Modlin's research materials on Eleanor.
This collection is organized into four series:
I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
II. CORRESPONDENCE
III. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES
IV. RESEARCH FILES OF CHARLES MODLIN
The Papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
The Eleanor Copenhaver Anderson papers were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection in 2008 and 2015 by Marjorie Modlin, widow of the Sherwood Anderson scholar Charles Modlin.
Women -- Employment -- United States -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Anderson, Eleanor Copenhaver, d. 1985; Copenhaver, Laura Scherer, 1868?-1940; Marion College (Marion, Va.) -- History; Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A. -- History
Related materials are in the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
  - General1948-51, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical articles by Margaret Ripley Wolfe1992-93 (Box 1, Folder 1a)
  - Clippings1922-62, undated (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
  - Address and telephone booksundated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Business cardsundated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Daily Reminder" diaries1929-33 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Death1985 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Education
    - General1917-33 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Masters Thesis: "Working Women in San Francisco, California," political science, Columbia University[original and photocopy]1933 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
  - Family
    - Copenhaver family and Rosemont Weavers1901-84, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Sherwood Anderson's Secret Love Letters: For Eleanor, a Letter a Day, edited by Ray Lewis White, LSU Press and Sherwood Anderson's Love Letters to Eleanor Copenhaver Anderson, edited by Charles E. Modlin, University of Georgia Press1991 and 1989 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - FBI file1938-54 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Financial1922-23 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Oral history interview by Mary Frederickson, Southern Oral History Program, University of North Carolina: transcript1975 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Photographs1922-84, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE
  - Miscellaneous1922-72, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Copenhaver, Eleanor to Sherwood Anderson1932 (Box 2, Folder 6-10)
  - Copenhaver, Bascom Eugene(father)1920-23, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Copenhaver, John Randolph (brother)1921, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Copenhaver, Laura Lu Scherer (mother)1921-25, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Scherer, Minerva May (aunt)1918, 1921, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
- SERIES III. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES
  - Notes on Southern Louisiana for Kaiser Aluminum and Chemical CorporationJul 1956 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - YWCA of the U.S.A.
    - General1922-53, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Conferences
      - General1926-31, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Findings of the Southern Industrial Conference1940 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence
      - General1920-55 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - Leonard, Louise1923, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - Miscellaneous YWCA Secretaries1928-50, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - "The Glory of the Task: A Pageant of Woman's Growing Heritage" by Laura Scherer Copenhaver and Eleanor Copenhaver, The Womans Press1927 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Radio script for appearance on "Woman of Tomorrow" with Nancy CraigNov 1942 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Reference file on southern textile industry strikes1929-30 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Reports
      - Report of the Ford Study on the Rural-Industrial Section by Eleanor Copenhaver, Margaret Forsyth, Donald McConnell, Dorothy P. Gary, and Lois MacDonald1926 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - American Federation of Labor Convention1936 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Friendship Train, ItalyJan 1948 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - "Social Ideals" worship service, Winston-Salem YWCA1933 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Writings for YWCA1929-50 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- SERIES IV. RESEARCH FILES OF CHARLES MODLIN
  - Chronologyundated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence
    - with YWCA1975, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - re entry for Dictionary of Virginia Biography1993 (Box 2, Folder 8)